JOE: Many children on the autism
spectrum are dependent on prompts
provided by adults for staying on-task,
completing activities and transitioning
between activities in the home,
school and community environments.
But over reliance on prompting
should be avoided as this can
become habit-forming in itself.
BETH: Prompt dependency can be recognised
when the individual is not prepared
for anything, such as getting dressed
and ready to start the day, and they
are relying on being told what to do.
To reduce or prevent prompt dependency
there should always be a plan made for
fading it out and from the outset plans
should be set up to implement fading once
the behaviour has become more regulated.
JOE: By reducing prompts and
only using them when needed
the dependency can be reduced.
In the beginning using prompts can
help with all steps of a process,
but as time progresses an individual
should be encouraged to organise
their own checklist, getting them
to try to figure things out more.
BETH: This can be done by
telling them to get dressed but
leaving them to choose the steps.
This can then be expanded to what to
do to start the day, such as ‘it’s
time to get up and get ready’ and
the rest is up to them following
their own checklist or timetable.
JOE: It’s a gradual process to move
an individual from intense prompt
dependence to self-sufficiency and
as this process begins, there should
be time factored in to encourage
the thinking process, rather than
immediately correcting the individual.
BETH: There is no one way of breaking
prompt dependency in autism, and
any changes a parent or carer
makes will probably reflect in the
behaviour of the child or individual.
However, the goal in every instance
is to encourage the individual
with autism to become more
independent in problem solving.